

Andrea Dal Pozzolo, PhD

Born in Schio (Italy) on August 19, 1987 Address: Oberdorfstrasse 13, 8107 Buchs-Zurich, Switzerland +41795799135 • dalpozz@gmail.com • www.linkedin.com/in/dalpozz

SUMMARY

I'm passionate about data and I define myself a Data Scientist: I'm an expert in Machine Learning, Data Mining and statistical techniques. I'm also interested in Actuarial Science and the application of statistical models in finance and business to extract knowledge from data.

EDUCATION

Université Libre de Bruxelles, Brussels, Belgium

Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.) in Computer Science

Jan 2012 - Dec 2015

- Thesis: Adaptive Machine Learning for Credit Card Fraud Detection
- · Adviser: Prof. Gianluca Bontempi
- Research areas: Machine Learning, Data Mining, Statistics and Fraud Detection.

Università di Bologna, Bologna, Italy

Master of Science (M.S.) in Applied Statistics and Actuarial Science

• Thesis: Comparison of Data Mining Techniques for Insurance Claim Prediction

• Final grade: 110/110 Summa Cum Laude

Bachelor of Science (B.S.) in Statistics for Finance and Insurance

Sep 2009 – Dec 2011

Sep 2009 – Dec 2011

• Second year at University of Glasgow (UK), Erasmus student

• Final grade: 110/110 Summa Cum Laude

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Politecnico di Milano, Milan, Italy

Visiting researcher at Dipartimento Elettronica e Informazione (DEI) Apr 2015 – Jun 2015

· Supervisors: Prof. Giacomo Boracchi

• Research areas: Credit Card Fraud Detection, Concept Drift, Active Learning.

University of Notre Dame, Notre Dame, Indiana, USA

Visiting researcher at Data Inference Analytics and Learning Lab (DIAL). May 2014 – Jun 2014

• Supervisors: Prof. Nitesh V Chawla

• Research areas: Unbalanced Classification, Concept Drift, Data Streams.

ACADEMIC AWARDS

BruFence project (total 1M 192K €), Innoviris (Brussels Region).	2015 - 2018
Doctiris PhD scholarship (320K €), Innoviris (Brussels Region).	2012 - 2015
Travel Grant for 2015 IJCNN conference (800 \$), IEEE	Jul 2015
Travel Grant for research collaborations (1500 €), Université Libre de Bruxelles	Apr 2015
Master Thesis scholarship (2000 €), Università di Bologna	Sep 2011
Erasmus mundus exchange scholarship (3000 €) ,Università di Bologna	Sep 2007

WORK EXPERIENCE

Ernst & Young, Zurich, Switzerland

Quantitative Consultant | Financial Services Advisory - Risk

Since Apr 2016

- Application of Machine Learning algorithms for conduct risk (fraud detection).
- · Credit and Market risk modelling for major Swiss Banks.
- · VaR and ES model auditing.

VASCO Data Security, Wemmel, Belgium

Decision Analytics Consultant

Jan 2016 – Mar 2016

- Implementation of Fraud Detection Systems based on Machine Learning algorithms.
- Definition of factors used by business rules for fraud prevention.
- Development of a Link Analysis application supporting fraud investigations.

Machine Learning Group - ULB, Brussels, Belgium

Researcher

Jan 2012 – Dec 2015

- Development of Machine Learning algorithms for Fraud Detection in credit cards.
- Collaboration with the fraud detection team of Worldline S.A (Brussels, Belgium).
- Supervision and coaching of master students.

Directa Sim, Turin, Italy

Analyst Aug 2009 – Jul 2011

- Supervision of VisualTrader development (online stock trading platform).
- Development of trading systems and market scanners.
- Customer support for the trading platform.

Allianz, Milan, Italy

Life actuary assistant

Nov 2008 - Feb 2009

- Balance analysis and report according to US GAAP and IFRS regulation (HB2).
- Gained a basic working knowledge of Moses and Prohet software.
- Worked in a team of 5 people having balance deadline to respect.

Absolute Quality, Glasgow, Scotland

Computer Game tester/translator

Oct 2007 - Nov 2007

- Translation in Italian and consistency with English.
- Develop analytical ability making sure that transcript mach my report.

Riccardo's restaurant, London, England

Waiter

Jun 2005 – Sep 2005

- Self-funded study and work experience in London for three months.
- Demonstrated my ability to adapt and thrive in new and different environments.

IT SKILLS R, Python, SAS, SQL, HTML, Java, C++, SPSS, LATEX, Microsoft Office suite (ECDL licence).

SOFTWARE Developed an R package called *unbalanced* for classification with unbalanced distributions.

PUBLICATIONS

<u>A. Dal Pozzolo</u>, O. Caelen, and G. Bontempi, "When is undersampling effective in unbalanced classification tasks?," in *Machine Learning and Knowledge Discovery in Databases (ECML-PKDD)*, Porto, Portugal, 2015.

<u>A. Dal Pozzolo</u>, O. Caelen, R. A Johnson and G. Bontempi, "Calibrating Probability with Undersampling for Unbalanced Classification," in *Proceedings of 2015 IEEE Symposium Series on Computational Intelligence (SSCI)*, Cape Town, South Africa, 2015.

<u>A. Dal Pozzolo</u>, G. Boracchi, O. Caelen, C. Alippi and G. Bontempi, "Credit Card Fraud Detection and Concept-Drift Adaptation with Delayed Supervised Information," in *Proceedings of 2015 International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN)*, Killarney, Ireland, 2015.

<u>A. Dal Pozzolo</u>, O. Caelen, Y. Le Borgne, S. Waterschoot, and G. Bontempi, "Learned lessons in credit card fraud detection from a practitioner perspective," *Expert Systems with Applications*, vol. 41, no. 10, pp. 4915–4928, 2014.

<u>A. Dal Pozzolo</u>, R. A Johnson, O. Caelen, S. Waterschoot, N. V Chawla, and G. Bontempi, "Using HDDT to avoid instances propagation in unbalanced and evolving data streams," in *Proceedings of 2014 International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN)*, Beijing, China, 2014.

<u>A. Dal Pozzolo</u>, O. Caelen, S. Waterschoot, and G. Bontempi, "Racing for unbalanced methods selection," in *Proceedings of the 14th International Conference on Intelligent Data Engineering and Automated Learning (IDEAL)*, Hefei, China, 2013.

LANGUAGES Italian: Native language.

English: Fluent (speaking, reading, writing).

French: Fluent (speaking, reading). Intermediate (writing).

German: Beginner (speaking, reading).

INTERESTS Cycling, Basketball, Economics, Digital photography.

REFERENCES Available upon request.

[Last update on 2016-06-11]